<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Converted from ALTO XML</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Converted from ALTO XML to TEI</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Original ALTO XML file</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="page" n="1">
        <pb n="1" xml:id="Page_1" />
        <p><persName>Edward S. Holden</persName>, LLD. <lb /><persName>Marco Polo</persName>'s Adventures <lb />The Greatest Traveller the World <lb />has seen <lb />The Century Magazine <lb /><date>October, 1900</date> <lb />PL-E-5:11 <lb />75</p>
      </div>
      <div type="page" n="2">
        <pb n="2" xml:id="Page_2" />
        <p><persName>MARCO POLO</persName>'S ADVENTURES. <lb />THE GREATEST TRAVELER THE WORLD HAS SEEN. <lb />By <persName>Edward S. Holden</persName>, LL.D. <lb />as <lb />ever he may have thought of it, he was <lb />imprisoned for about a year in <placeName>Genoa</placeName>, <lb />in the company of a professional man <lb />of letters. Here he dictated a long <lb />account of his travels in the kingdoms <lb />of the <placeName>East</placeName> and of the marvels that he <lb />had seen. <lb />His book is of the first importance to <lb />historical geographers. It is of the high- <lb />est interest, also, as a human document. <lb />It is, moreover, one of the great story- <lb />books of the world. It not only throws <lb />a flood of light upon the state of <placeName>south- <lb />ern Europe</placeName> in his time, but it opens the <lb /><placeName>East</placeName>, till then unknown. <lb />The amazing conquests of the Mongols <lb />under <persName>Jenghiz Khan</persName> and his successors <lb />brought the <placeName>East</placeName>, from the steppes of <placeName>Rus- <lb />sia</placeName> to the <placeName>Pacific</placeName>, under a single dynasty. <lb />Whoever had a Tablet of Authority from <lb />the <persName>Grand Khan</persName> could travel unmolested <lb />From Winsor's "<persName>Columbus</persName>." <lb />from the <placeName>Oxus</placeName> to the <placeName>Hoang-Ho</placeName>. <persName>Marco</persName> <lb /><persName>Marco Polo</persName>. <lb /><persName>Polo</persName> lived at precisely the right time. Not <lb />long after his death, the <placeName>Farther East</placeName> be- <lb />O <lb />F all books of travel and adven- <lb />came closed to all Europeans. The Mos- <lb />ture, the book of <persName>Ser Marco Polo</persName>, <lb />lems succeeded the Mongols as rulers in <lb />the Venetian, concerning the <lb /><placeName>Central Asia</placeName>, and they stopped the road <lb />kingdoms and the marvels of the <placeName>East</placeName> <lb />to <placeName>China</placeName> like a wall. No European could <lb />is the most famous and the most interest- <lb />pass. This road was not opened until the <lb />ing. He left <placeName>Venice</placeName> in the year <date>1271</date>, and <lb /><date>sixteenth century</date>, when <placeName>China</placeName> was redis- <lb />returned to his old home twenty-six years <lb />covered, so to say. <lb />later. In the meantime he had traversed <lb /><persName>Marco</persName> was a merchant-and so he tells <lb />the provinces of <placeName>Persia</placeName> and the <placeName>nearer</placeName> <lb />us of trade; he was a soldier-and he <lb /><placeName>East</placeName>, crossed the high steppes of the <placeName>Pa- <lb />mir</placeName> region and the whole length of <placeName>China</placeName>, <lb />tells us of the wars of the Tartars; he was <lb />a court official-and thus we have an ac- <lb />and resided at the Court of the <persName>Grand</persName> <lb />count of the government; he was the ruler <lb /><persName>Khan</persName> of <placeName>Tartary</placeName>, for many years, as one <lb />of a great city-and we have from him a <lb />of his trusted officers. For a part of the <lb />picture of the Chinese people in their <lb />time he was the Governor of a great Chi- <lb />homes; he was the trusted ambassador of <lb />nese city, and he was often intrusted by <lb />the <persName>Emperor</persName> to foreign parts-and he has <lb />the <persName>Khan</persName> with important missions to dis- <lb />described many provinces of the remote <lb />tant parts of the Empire, and even to for- <lb /><placeName>East</placeName> from personal experience; others he <lb />eign countries. <lb />describes from hearsay. Many names <lb />By a lucky chance, as he himself styles <lb />now familiar-the <placeName>Pamir</placeName>, <placeName>Madagascar</placeName>, <lb />it, he was permitted by the <persName>Khan</persName> to re- <lb />and so forth-appear in his book for the <lb />turn to <placeName>Venice</placeName>, where he lived the life <lb />first time. <lb />of a merchant prince, glad to converse <lb />This resolute, intelligent, and sober- <lb />about his extraordinary adventures, but <lb />minded man spent the best years of his <lb />with no thought of writing them out for <lb />life under absolutely unique conditions. <lb />future generations to delight in. By a <lb />Some parts of his story are retold here, <lb />chance still more fortunate for us, what- <lb />almost in his own words.* <lb />*Making use of Colonel <persName>Yule</persName>'s scholarly text and notes.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="page" n="3">
        <pb n="3" xml:id="Page_3" />
        <p>It was in the <lb /><placeName>Asia</placeName> was un- <lb /><placeName>Tartary</placeName> a European monk (<persName>De Rubri- <lb />quis</persName>) found, in <date>1253</date>, Russians, Greeks, <lb /><persName>Shakespeare</persName>'s. <persName>Marco Polo</persName> was filled <lb />year <date>1271</date> that <lb />known to Euro- <lb />with amazement at the civilization of the <lb /><persName>Marco</persName>, then a lad <lb />peans, except the <lb />Hungarians, and even "a Frenchman <lb />Chinese. <lb />seventeen years <lb />very few routes <lb />from <placeName>Paris</placeName>." These were sometimes fu- <lb />Let us remember that the first transla- <lb />old, started with <lb />along which trad- <lb />gitives from justice, but oftener pris- <lb />tion of the Bible into English was made <lb />his father and his <lb />ers traveled. The <lb />oners taken by the Tartars, who sent <lb />in <date>1382</date>; that <persName>Chaucer</persName>, the Father of the <lb />uncle on his long <lb />silks and carpets <lb />them to their cities to teach the arts <lb />English language, died in <date>1400</date>. French <lb />journey of three <lb />of <placeName>Persia</placeName>, for ex- <lb />of jewelry, weaving, house-building, and <lb />was the language of the law-courts of <lb />years to <placeName>Peking</placeName>. <lb />ample, had been <lb />so forth. <lb /><placeName>London</placeName> until <date>1362</date>. A few of the colleges <lb />Nearly every step <lb />known in <placeName>Europe</placeName> <lb />The western half of <placeName>Asia</placeName> was thus not <lb />of <placeName>Oxford</placeName> and <placeName>Cambridge</placeName> were founded <lb />of the way was <lb />for more than a <lb />utterly unknown. But its eastern regions <lb />before this time, but they were monaster- <lb />full of danger. <lb />Head of <persName>Marco Polo</persName>'s Sheep (Ovis <persName>poli</persName>) <lb />thousand years. <lb />On the sea they <lb />For very many <lb />traveled in frail sailing vessels, with no <lb />years the glass- and gold-work of <placeName>Venice</placeName> <lb />compass to guide them-for the com- <lb />had been sent to the <placeName>East</placeName>. A few Euro- <lb />pass was then unknown in <placeName>Europe</placeName>, al- <lb />pean merchants had trading-houses on the <lb />although well known in <placeName>China</placeName>. By day <lb /><placeName>Black Sea</placeName>, in <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>, in <placeName>Bagdad</placeName>, <lb />they coasted along from headland to <lb />in <placeName>Bassorah</placeName>: and there they sent their <lb />headland. By night they anchored near <lb />goods for exchange. Silks came to <placeName>Europe</placeName> <lb />the shore when they could find a sheltered <lb />from <placeName>China</placeName>; muslin (from <lb />bay, or else steered timidly by the stars. <lb /><placeName>Mosul</placeName>); calico from <placeName>Calicut</placeName>, in <placeName>India</placeName>. Our <lb />Contrary winds delayed them, or drove <lb />ancestors, before the Crusaders had <lb />them out of their course. Their vessels <lb />brought back with them the spices of the <lb />were small affairs, not able to buffet <lb /><placeName>East</placeName>, used no seasoning in their food ex- <lb />storms. The seas they traversed <lb />cept salt. Pepper, cloves, nutmegs, cin- <lb />swarmed with pirates and enemies. <lb />namon, etc., were unknown. Common <lb />On land they made their journeys on <lb />drugs, like camphor and laudanum, had <lb />foot, on horseback, and on camels, al- <lb />to be brought from the <placeName>Orient</placeName>. Most <lb />ways traveling with caravans, for fear of <lb />jewels came from <placeName>India</placeName>, too-diamonds, <lb />robbers. When they came to a river they <lb />rubies, emeralds, pearls. The Crusades <lb />crossed it as best they could. After more <lb />(<date>1095-1270</date>) opened the trade between <lb />than three years of journeying they at <lb />the <placeName>East</placeName> and the <placeName>West</placeName>, and made the <lb />last reached <placeName>Peking</placeName>. They had traversed <lb />daily life of <placeName>Europe</placeName> a new thing in very <lb /><placeName>Armenia</placeName>, visited <placeName>Bagdad</placeName>, on the <placeName>Tigris</placeName>: <lb />many ways. <lb /><placeName>Hormuz</placeName>, at the mouth of the <placeName>Persian</placeName> <lb />Christian missionaries had spread over <lb />Gulf: crossed all <placeName>Persia</placeName> and <placeName>Turkistan</placeName>: <lb />a large part of the <placeName>nearer East</placeName>. There <lb />climbed the <lb />were bishops <lb />high passes of <lb />and churches <lb />the <placeName>Himalaya</placeName> <lb />in <placeName>Turkistan</placeName> <lb />Mountains to <lb />as early as <lb />the elevated <lb /><date>A. D. 334</date>. A <lb />plains of the <lb />whole tribe of <lb /><placeName>Pamir</placeName> region; <lb />Turkomans <lb />plodded across <lb />became Chris- <lb />the vast desert <lb />tians about <lb />of <placeName>Gobi</placeName> and so <lb /><date>A. D. 1000</date>. <lb />The Father and Uncle of <persName>Marco Polo</persName> Leaving <placeName>Constantinople</placeName>. (From a MS. of the <date>XIV. Century</date>.) <lb />through all <lb />There were <lb /><placeName>China</placeName> to <placeName>Pe- <lb />king</placeName>. Their <lb />Christians in <lb /><placeName>India</placeName>, too, from <lb />were quite unvisited. <placeName>China</placeName> was barely <lb />ies rather than halls of learning. Mat- <lb />home coming, <lb />the earliest <lb />known by name. <placeName>Japan</placeName> had not been <lb />ters were worse in <placeName>France</placeName>. The streets <lb />years after- <lb />times, and it is <lb />heard of at all. <lb />of <placeName>Paris</placeName> were not paved (as were the <lb />wards, was by <lb />very probable <lb />These partly known or wholly unknown <lb />streets of Chinese cities), and they were <lb />a still longer <lb />that one of the <lb />people were as civilized as the people of <lb />unsafe at night on account of wolves and <lb />route. <lb />Apostles- <lb />contemporary <placeName>Europe</placeName>, though in differ- <lb />robbers. <placeName>Bagdad</placeName>, <placeName>Cordova</placeName>, <placeName>Damascus</placeName>, <lb />In those <lb /><persName>Saint Thomas</persName> <lb />ent lines. The Persians, for instance, <lb /><placeName>Tangiers</placeName>, <placeName>Samarkand</placeName>, and <placeName>Bokhara</placeName> were <lb />days, six hun- <lb />-preached <lb />were learned, polite, industrious. The <lb />seats of learning. <lb />dred years ago, <lb />there. In the <lb />Hindus had a great architecture, a great <lb />With these brief accounts of the state <lb />nearly all of <lb />Tower at the Corner of the Wall of the Tartar City. <lb />great towns of <lb />literature, poems like Homer's, plays like <lb />of <placeName>Europe</placeName> in <persName>Marco Polo</persName>'s times, let us</p>
      </div>
      <div type="page" n="4">
        <pb n="4" xml:id="Page_4" />
        <p>hear what he has to say of <placeName>China</placeName> and the <lb />heard; so that the <persName>Emperor</persName> and all such <lb />a height of more than ten paces. The <lb />and runs his three miles. And in this <lb />Chinese. <lb />as heard his story were surprised, and <lb />streets are so straight and wide that you <lb />way the <persName>Emperor</persName> receives dispatches with <lb />said: 'If this young man live, he will <lb />can see right along them from end to end, <lb />news from places ten days' journey off in <lb />How the <persName>Great Khan</persName> received the Travel- <lb />assuredly come to be a person of great <lb />and from one gate to another. Thus the <lb />one day and a night; and that is no small <lb />ers at <placeName>Peking</placeName>, <date>A. D. 1275</date>. <lb />worth and ability.' Thereafter <persName>Messer</persName> <lb />whole city is arranged in squares, just <lb />matter. In fact, in the fruit season, many <lb />"When the two brothers and <persName>Mark</persName> had <lb /><persName>Marco</persName> abode in the <persName>Khan</persName>'s employment <lb />like a chess-board, in a manner so per- <lb />a time fruit is gathered one morning, and <lb />arrived in that great city, they went to the <lb />some seventeen years, continually going <lb />fect and masterly that it is impossible <lb />the next day it reaches the <persName>Great Khan</persName>, <lb />Imperial Palace, and there they found the <lb />and coming, hither and thither, on the <lb />to give a description that should do it <lb />a distance of ten days' journey off." <lb />sovereign, attended by a great company <lb />missions that were intrusted to him by <lb />justice." <lb />How the <persName>Great Khan</persName> causes Stores of <lb />of barons. So they bent the knee before <lb />the <persName>Lord</persName>, and sometimes on his own <lb />How the <persName>Khan</persName>'s Posts and Runners are <lb />Grain to be made, to help his <lb />private affairs. And as he knew all the <lb />sped through many Lands and <lb />People withal, in Time <lb />sovereign's ways, like a sensible man, he <lb />took much pains to gather knowledge, <lb />Provinces. <lb />of Dearth. <lb />and then, on his return to Court, he <lb />"You must know that the <persName>Emperor</persName> <lb />"From this city of <placeName>Cambaluc</placeName> proceed <lb />would relate everything in regular order, <lb />many roads and highways, and each road <lb />buys large quantities of grain and has it <lb />and thus the <persName>Emperor</persName> came to hold him <lb />stored in all his provinces. And by this <lb />receives the name of the province to <lb />in great love and favor. And thus it <lb />which it leads-a very sensible plan. And <lb />providence his people can never suffer <lb />came about that <persName>Messer Marco Polo</persName> had <lb />from dearth. He does this over his whole <lb />the messengers of the <persName>King</persName> find at every <lb />knowledge of, or had actually visited, a <lb />twenty-five miles of their journey a sta- <lb />Empire, according to the wants and ne- <lb />greater number of the different countries <lb />tion. At each of the stations used by the <lb />cessities of his people." <lb />of the world than any other man." <lb />messengers there is a large and handsome <lb />Of the Charity of the <persName>Emperor</persName> to the Poor. <lb /><persName>Marco</persName> arrived at the Imperial Court <lb />building furnished with fine beds. Even <lb />"You see, he causes selection to be made <lb />in <date>1275</date>. He was an official of the Court <lb />if a king were to arrive at one of these he <lb />of a number of families in the city, and <lb />at least as early as <date>1277</date>, when he was <lb />would find himself well-lodged. At these <lb />each family he causes to be supplied with <lb />sent on an embassy to <placeName>Tibet</placeName>, <placeName>Yunnan</placeName>, and <lb />stations, moreover, there are two hundred <lb />wheat sufficient for the whole year. And <lb />northern <placeName>Burma</placeName>. For more than three <lb />horses standing ready for the use of the <lb />this he never fails to do every year. He <lb />years he was Governor of the great Chi- <lb />messengers. In sooth, this is a thing done <lb />also provides the poor with clothes." <lb />nese city of <placeName>Yang-Chow</placeName>; and we know <lb />on the greatest scale of magnificence that <lb />of at least three other missions of his: to <lb />ever was seen. And you must know that, <lb />Concerning the Great River <placeName>Yang-Tse- <lb />Portrait of <persName>Kublai Khan</persName>, from a Chinese Engraving. <lb /><placeName>Karakorum</placeName>, in <placeName>north Mongolia</placeName>; to south- <lb />by the <persName>Great Khan</persName>'s orders, there has <lb />Kiang</placeName>. <lb />ern <placeName>Cochin-China</placeName>; and to southern <placeName>India</placeName>. <lb />been established between those post- <lb />"I assure you this river flows so far <lb />him, prostrating themselves to the ground. <lb />He returned to <placeName>Venice</placeName> in <date>1295 or 1296</date>, by <lb />houses at every three miles a little fort, in <lb />and traverses so many countries and cities <lb />Then the <persName>Lord</persName> bade them stand up and <lb />sea, visiting <placeName>Sumatra</placeName>, <placeName>India</placeName>, and <placeName>Persia</placeName> <lb />which dwell the people who act as the <lb />that, in good sooth, there pass and repass <lb />treated them with great honor, showing <lb />on the way. <lb /><persName>Emperor</persName>'s foot-runners. Every one of <lb />on its waters more wealth and merchan- <lb />great pleasure at their coming. And <lb />Of the City of <placeName>Cambaluc</placeName> (<placeName>Peking</placeName>). <lb />those runners wears a great wide belt, set <lb />dise than on all the seas of <placeName>Christendom</placeName> <lb />next, spying <persName>Mark</persName>, who was then a young <lb />all over with bells, so that as they run <lb />put together. It seems more like a sea <lb />"You must know," says <persName>Marco Polo</persName>'s <lb />their bells are heard jingling a long way <lb />than a river. <persName>Messer Marco Polo</persName> said <lb />gallant, he asked who was that in their <lb />scribe, "that for three months in the year <lb />company. 'Sire,' said his father, <persName>Messer</persName> <lb />the <persName>Great Khan</persName> resides in the capital city <lb />off. And thus, on reaching the post, the <lb />that he once beheld fifteen thousand <lb /><persName>Nicolo</persName>, ''tis my son.' 'Welcome is he, <lb />of <placeName>Cathay</placeName>, which is called <placeName>Cambaluc</placeName>. In <lb />runner finds another man all ready to take <lb />vessels at one time. And you may judge, <lb />too,' quoth the <persName>Emperor</persName>. Now it came <lb />that city stands his great palace, and <lb />his place, so that the new man sets off <lb />if this city has such a number, how many <lb />to pass that <persName>Marco</persName> sped wondrously in <lb />now I will tell you what it is like. It is <lb />there must be alto- <lb />learning the customs of the Tartars, as <lb />gether, considering <lb />enclosed all round by a great wall, form- <lb />that on the banks of <lb />well as their language, their manner of <lb />ing a square, each side of which is a mile <lb />this river there are <lb />writing, and their practice in war. And <lb />in length; that is to say, the whole com- <lb />more than sixteen <lb />he was discreet and prudent in every way, <lb />pass thereof is four miles. You must <lb />provinces and more <lb />so that the <persName>Emperor</persName> held him in great <lb />know that it is the greatest palace that <lb />than two hundred <lb />esteem. And so, when he discerned <persName>Mark</persName> <lb />ever was. The roof is very lofty, and the <lb />great cities, all pos- <lb />to have so much sense, he sent him on an <lb />walls are all covered with gold and sil- <lb />sessing vessels." <lb />embassy to a country that was a good <lb />ver, and on the ceiling, too, you see noth- <lb />six months' journey distant. When <persName>Mark</persName> <lb />ing but gold and silver and painting. The <lb />Of the Canals of the <lb />returned from his embassy, he presented <lb />hall of the palace is so large that it could <lb />Country. <lb />himself before the <persName>Emperor</persName>, and, after <lb />easily dine six thousand people; and it is <lb />Of the canals he <lb />making his report of the business with <lb />quite a marvel to see how many rooms <lb />says: "The <persName>Emperor</persName> <lb />which he was charged, he went on to <lb />there are besides. As regards the size of <lb />has caused wide and <lb />give an account, in a pleasant and intel- <lb />the city, it has a compass of twenty-four <lb />deep canals to be dug <lb />ligent manner, of all the novelties and <lb />miles, and it is four-square. And it is <lb />between river and riv- <lb />strange things that he had seen and <lb />all walled round with walls of earth, with <lb />Watch-Tower on the Wall of the Tartar City. <lb />er, lake and lake,</p>
      </div>
      <div type="page" n="5">
        <pb n="5" xml:id="Page_5" />
        <p>forming, as it were, rivers on which large <lb />cooked. <persName>Marco</persName> also described the moun- <lb />vessels can ply. And thus there is com- <lb />tain sheep of that region, whose horns are <lb />munication between each city and <placeName>Peking</placeName>, <lb />"a good four feet in length," and his story <lb />so that great vessels with their loads can <lb />was doubted. But the sheep are there to- <lb />go the whole way. A land road also ex- <lb />day, and they have even been named in <lb />ists; for the earth dug from these canals <lb />honor of the traveler Ovis <persName>poli</persName>. <lb />has been thrown up to form an embanked <lb />In another place he describes the "great <lb />road on either side." <lb />snakes and serpents" of the region. "You <lb />These bits of description are examples <lb />may be assured," he says, "that some of <lb />of the manner in which <persName>Marco Polo</persName> <lb />them are ten paces in length; some more, <lb />spoke of the country which he knew so <lb />some less. And in bulk they are equal <lb />well. They were the first intelligent ac- <lb />to a great cask. The mouth is large <lb />counts that came to <placeName>Europe</placeName> of the vast <lb />enough to swallow a man, and is gar- <lb />Empire of <placeName>China</placeName>-the <placeName>Farther East</placeName>-and <lb />nished with great pointed teeth." This <lb />they were a revelation. They were re- <lb />sounds like a very large story: serpents <lb />ceived with a doubting wonder, and it is <lb />more than thirty feet long and as big as <lb />only within the <date>present century</date> that we <lb />a hogshead! But it is quite true: for the <lb />have learned how accurate they are. In <lb />"serpents" were nothing but crocodiles, <lb />The <persName>Great Khan</persName> Gives a Tablet of Authority to the Two Brothers. (From a MS. of the <date>XIV. Century</date>.) <lb />his own time many of them were regard- <lb />which <persName>Marco</persName> saw for the first time. He <lb />ed as the merest traveler's tales. <lb />discovered that the fabled salamander, <lb />When <persName>Marco</persName> crossed the great plain <lb />that lives in fire, was no animal, but mere- <lb />of the <placeName>Pamir</placeName>-"the roof of the world"- <lb />ly mineral Asbestos. As with these sto- <lb />he says "The region is so lofty and cold <lb />ries, so with others. The more we learn <lb />that you do not see any birds flying. And <lb />about the countries that he visited, the <lb />I must notice also that because of this <lb />truer we find his descriptions of them. <lb />great cold, fire does not burn so brightly <lb />The book of <persName>Marco Polo</persName>, the Venetian, <lb />nor give out so much heat as usual, nor <lb />was translated into many languages, and <lb />does it cook food so effectually." <lb />it was current in many countries. <persName>Colum- <lb />bus</persName> knew it well, and when he sailed west- <lb />What an extravagant story this must <lb />ward to "<placeName>Cathay</placeName>" he bore a letter from <lb />have seemed to the people of <placeName>Venice</placeName>, who <lb />the <persName>Pope</persName> to the <persName>Grand Khan</persName> of <placeName>Tartary</placeName>. <lb />lived at the level of the sea, where water <lb />To the day of his death he believed that <lb />boils at 212 degrees. On the <placeName>Pamir</placeName>, <lb /><placeName>Cuba</placeName> was the <placeName>Cipango (Japan)</placeName> of <persName>Polo</persName>. <lb />12,000 feet above sea, the boiling point of <lb />If it had not been for <persName>Polo</persName>'s discoveries, <lb />water is about 192 degrees, and an egg <lb /><persName>Columbus</persName> would never have started. <lb />boiled there for three minutes is quite un-</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
